<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Societal Wellbeing | Ellen Considine</title>
    <link>https://EllenConsidine.github.io/tags/societal-wellbeing/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://EllenConsidine.github.io/tags/societal-wellbeing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Societal Wellbeing</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://EllenConsidine.github.io/media/icon_hu68170e94a17a2a43d6dcb45cf0e8e589_3079_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Societal Wellbeing</title>
      <link>https://EllenConsidine.github.io/tags/societal-wellbeing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Principled Negotiation and the Ethos of Public Health</title>
      <link>https://EllenConsidine.github.io/post/public-health-ethos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://EllenConsidine.github.io/post/public-health-ethos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am currently reading a book on negotiation called &lt;em&gt;Getting to Yes&lt;/em&gt;, written by members of the Harvard Negotiation Project. One of the opening chapters describes positional bargaining: two sides starting from places of disagreement and inching their way closer by making small concessions in turn. The authors describe how problematic this process is: it is inefficient, commonly leads to unwise outcomes (good for neither side), and can harm relationships between parties. Instead, the book presents a case for principled negotiation, founded on separating the people (negotiators) from the problem, focusing on interests instead of positions, inventing options for mutual gain, and insisting on use of objective criteria. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pon.harvard.edu/daily/negotiation-skills-daily/principled-negotiation-focus-interests-create-value/&#34;&gt;Here is a nice summary&lt;/a&gt;, for those interested in learning more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bring this book up to motivate presentation of my principles. Nearly everything we do in our professional and personal lives is a negotiation of some kind. It is important to establish what we believe so that we can work with others to identify common ground and develop pragmatic solutions to our problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listening to the news and having conversations with other people, it is clear that there are foundationally diverse beliefs about how human civilization should look, and how we should get there (if the belief is that we aren&amp;rsquo;t already there). I have come to the unoriginal conclusion that the largest discrepancy in how people think and act is described by the weight an individual mentally assigns to their personal freedoms in comparison with the freedoms of others, and to what extent they believe we should rely on governmental authorities to enforce the balance of individuals&amp;rsquo; freedoms. This discrepancy has obvious ties to the arena of public health, where large and complex problems such as infectious diseases and environmental pollution bring tensions between individual freedoms and collective sacrifice to light. In fact, while pondering my beliefs and their implications, I ran across the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apha.org/-/media/files/pdf/membergroups/ethics/code_of_ethics.ashx&#34;&gt;Public Health Code of Ethics&lt;/a&gt; by the American Public Health Association (APHA) and determined this to be the most clear articulation of my principles that I have ever found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an excerpt from this Code of Ethics [page 3, bolding is mine], defining what it means for humans to flourish:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Flourishing does not focus so much on biological function as on &lt;strong&gt;the social conditions of capability and opportunity&lt;/strong&gt; upon which health itself and many other goods depend. Flourishing refers to what individuals and communities experience when institutional and cultural structures create the opportunity for people to realize a wide range of potential capabilities inherent in all human beings. Flourishing occurs when &lt;strong&gt;capabilities for agency, creativity, intelligence, understanding, emotional engagement, and other positive human potentialities take shape in the form of lives well lived&lt;/strong&gt;. As such, we take a life course perspective that examines public health issues from maternal and child health into old age while &lt;strong&gt;recognizing specific vulnerabilities&lt;/strong&gt; at the extremes of age. The term human flourishing also underscores the &lt;strong&gt;relational interdependence&lt;/strong&gt; among human beings, which is expressed in virtually all social and cultural activity and fits well with the contemporary understanding of the social determinants of health. &lt;strong&gt;The preconditions of everyone’s health are communal and systemic&lt;/strong&gt;, and the field of public health must address them as such. Human flourishing is thus consonant with a social-relational, rather than an exclusively individualistic, interpretation of key values such as human rights, liberty, equality, and social and environmental justice that play a vital role in contemporary public health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The opposite of human flourishing is&lt;/strong&gt; not only disease or ill health but also domination, inequity, discrimination, exploitation, exclusion, suffering, and despair: in a word, &lt;strong&gt;the stultification and denial of optimal human self-realization and thriving human communities.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this definition, it is clear that public health is all about giving people opportunities to live fulfilling lives. In fact, it seems that the goal is to maximize individual freedoms, within the bounds of not denying other individuals their freedoms. Later in this document, there is also an explicit discussion of responsibilities towards future generations and other organisms in our environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recognize that these statements may all seem abstract. However, I think that before moving to more specific examples, we need to identify foundational points of agreement, such as the preciousness of self-realization. Then, we can build upon those foundations and deal with higher-level disagreements (e.g. differences in perspective about how we best allow people to self-realize) as they come. In the midst of extreme political polarization and ever-increasing complexity of societal problems, I believe that this kind of principled negotiation is necessary to develop a modern society that is just and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you too are someone who is interested in helping address large and complex issues in our society, I encourage you to articulate: what are your principles?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Having an Impact, Part 2</title>
      <link>https://EllenConsidine.github.io/post/impact-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://EllenConsidine.github.io/post/impact-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Effective Altruism (EA) / 80,000 Hours philosophy has guided many of my thoughts and actions over the past 4+ years. In this post, my goal is to articulate some of the most important and generalizable aspects of my EA journey so far. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet encountered the EA / 80,000 Hours movement, I recommend checking out Part 1!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;overall-reflections&#34;&gt;Overall Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internalizing many of the EA / 80,000 Hours ideas guided me into the field of environmental public health / biostatistics, no question. This semester, I’ve really enjoyed seeing the close alignment between these fields / movements in my introductory public health classes. Of course, there are countless other fields in which one can pursue having a positive impact along the lines of the EA literature. I can simply confirm that I am glad to have made decisions in accordance with this paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, critically examining one&amp;rsquo;s overall impact is not for the faint of heart. Some of the most distressing loops I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten stuck in over the years include questioning whether certain career / life opportunities are worth their associated environmental costs (such as plane flights) and financial costs (i.e. would it be better to donate money now to a cause than to invest in my personal career capital, which may help that or another cause in the long term?), balancing avoidance of the &amp;ldquo;white savior complex&amp;rdquo; with the potential for bringing in funding and technical expertise to under-resourced areas, and deciding how much to focus on science vs. public policy more directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;balancing-different-kinds-of-good&#34;&gt;Balancing Different Kinds of Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crux of the matter is that nothing we can do is 100% good by all definitions. Even determining if our actions have net positive impact is challenging / impossible. Was my flight to Nepal to volunteer with Engineers Without Borders net positive? In addition to the work that we did and the personal connections we made, all of the learning I did over that summer has helped me to build a more resilient mental framework about global inequities and to more realistically compare pathways for reducing global poverty. But will my having that knowledge end up being more helpful to others than if I’d simply donated the money for my plane ticket to one of the most cost-effective charitable organizations? Wouldn’t my environmental footprint be so much smaller if, instead of going to graduate school and pursuing a professional career, I went and lived off the grid in a tiny cabin in the woods? But then I would be reducing my opportunities to interact with and help others&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The what-ifs are endless, and it’s easy to feel overwhelmed if you let yourself dive too deep too often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the &lt;em&gt;timing&lt;/em&gt; of individual giving, I have found &lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/should-you-wait/&#34;&gt;this 80,000 Hours framework&lt;/a&gt; to be helpful. But that still doesn’t necessarily help us distinguish between / balance different types of “good”. Any model that we make to try and quantify and compare different kinds of impacts will have massive uncertainty and subjectivity because there are so many things that are difficult and/or rely on philosophical judgements to quantify. How do we value investment in public K-12 education versus Medicare? Funding to conserve biodiversity versus to fight oppression based on race, gender, or sexual identity? Etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much as I enjoy building mathematical models to describe the world, I don&amp;rsquo;t believe there is a way to maximize good across all the areas of life and society that I care about. Ultimately, on an individual level we have to choose what cause(s) to prioritize based on personal affinity and potential for impact. On a societal level, I believe that democracy is one of our best tools for deciding fair allocation of resources, though even the best national democracy is likely to fall short when considering international and/or intergenerational issues, given lack of representation by all affected parties. This, in turn, highlights the importance of public education, as it can help a population to be aware of the plights of other people across space and time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fighting-the-white--privileged-savior-complex&#34;&gt;Fighting the White / Privileged Savior Complex&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest issues with the traditional EA paradigm is that it often assumes, or at least strongly implies, that people from privileged backgrounds can know and do what’s best for people in under-resourced situations. This can lead to ineffective or even harmful interventions, and also often perpetuates professional and socio-cultural power differentials between people in higher- and lower-income countries or communities within the same country. This problem is acknowledged (with links to more lengthy discussions) in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/faqs-criticism-objections#how-are-the-people-youre-trying-to-help-involved-in-the-decision-making&#34;&gt;Effective Altruism list of common objections&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experiences associated with Engineers Without Borders confronted me with related issues countless times, and in large part convinced me to pursue a career in which I could help gain knowledge and allocate resources on more systemic levels. However, as I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed with multiple professors and other respected mentors, the counterweight is that directly focusing on research or interventions in low-income areas can bring in much-needed funding from higher-income institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue will not disappear any time soon; I anticipate needing to re-evaluate my ability to provide assistance without overstepping in all my future projects. In general, I believe that people with lived experience and/or intimate expertise must be included (and ideally should lead) when making decisions regarding ways to promote causes such as poverty reduction and racial justice. I dive deeper into this last conviction in my &amp;ldquo;Reflections on Privilege in Higher Education&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;careers-in-science-vs-policy&#34;&gt;Careers in Science vs. Policy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is clearly a spectrum in terms of how long it takes our work to positively impact the lives of others. In terms of fields that I’m interested in: many technical problems in science (especially those focused on methodology) are not immediately relevant for helping other people (and thus may feel less impactful) in the way that pushing forward legislation in a government agency or working for a non-governmental organization can be. This can be disheartening for those of us who are motivated by a more personal connection to the impacts of our work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I sense (and have been told by respected mentors) that this is changing somewhat: many scientists are beginning to engage directly with decision makers. This trend is boosted by the increasing availability of near-real-time data sets (e.g. Covid-19 counts) and recognition that sorting through such data sets often requires scientific expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, while I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;ll continue to grapple with such questions for many years to come, I&amp;rsquo;m operating under the hope that by gaining a data science skill set grounded in public health applications, I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to strike a balance in my career between indirect and direct work to help others. Though I’m still very much in the midst of figuring this stuff out, my best advice to stay motivated (for anyone following a similar path) is to seek out opportunities to help others along the way, through mentoring, collaborating on applied projects, volunteering, or some combination of the above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;parting-thoughts&#34;&gt;Parting Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I have found the EA / 80,000 Hours framework to be useful in framing my individual pursuit of positive societal impact, I do not believe that this is the only way to make decisions leading to a meaningful life. For instance, I highly value others&amp;rsquo; decision to pursue careers in music and writing fiction. Art could be considered a different kind of positive impact, but I tend to see it as divergent from the traditional EA / 80,000 Hours path.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Having an Impact, Part 1</title>
      <link>https://EllenConsidine.github.io/post/impact-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://EllenConsidine.github.io/post/impact-part1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My views and aspirations for both my professional and my personal life have been profoundly influenced by the Effective Altruism (EA) / 80,000 Hours movement. This post is meant to introduce those who haven’t encountered this movement to it. See &amp;ldquo;On Having an Impact, Part 2&amp;rdquo; for some of my reflections in light of this overarching philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;intro-to-effective-altruism-and-80000-hours&#34;&gt;Intro to Effective Altruism and 80,000 Hours&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Instead of citing everything in the paragraphs below, I’m including a list of links at the end of this post, which I encourage you to explore!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core question of EA / 80,000 Hours is: &lt;strong&gt;how can I most effectively help other people, given finite resources?&lt;/strong&gt; There are many ways in which we can help others: directly and indirectly, material and non-material goods and services, in the short-term and in the long-term, concentrated and dispersed across individuals…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80,000 Hours often highlights the impact you can have in your career, but EA also encompasses the impact you can have by giving money to organizations which are doing good, engaging in advocacy, or helping others to increase their impact. Some of the key ideas promoted by EA / 80,000 Hours include focusing on cost-effectiveness, long-termism, personal fit, and collaboration with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost-effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt; means optimization of positive impact per dollar spent. To motivate this: it has been shown that the best global health interventions can be orders of magnitude more cost-effective than others. Thankfully, there are now organizations whose purpose is to determine the cost-effectiveness of different charitable organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EA / 80,000 Hours also argues that if we factor in the wellbeing of future generations, then &lt;strong&gt;long-term impacts&lt;/strong&gt; become more and more favorable. In terms of high-impact careers, this often translates into research- or policy-based vocations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding &lt;strong&gt;personal fit&lt;/strong&gt;, 80,000 hours makes a pretty strong case that we are most effective in jobs that align with our skills, interests, and personalities. However, they also discuss how individual abilities are most often built, not innate, so we can guide ourselves in certain directions over time if so we choose. While figuring out what kind(s) of work to pursue, they advocate “cheap” tests such as reaching out to others and trying things out on small scales. College is a great time to do this, as I discuss in &amp;ldquo;The Power of Showing Up and Reaching Out&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration&lt;/strong&gt; is crucial for addressing large-scale and/or complex problems. Although collaboration has not always been promoted as a core idea by the EA/80,000 Hours community, I am highlighting it here because of my personal belief in its importance. Some conclusions that stuck out to me from &lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/coordination/&#34;&gt;80,000 Hours’ article about collaboration&lt;/a&gt; are that to maximize coordination within a shared-aims community, we should:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prioritize upholding norms of kindness and honesty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invest in community capital&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be willing to specialize, explore, and even take opportunities with worse personal fit if they play to our comparative advantages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though there are many directions to take the above list of ideas, some actions that immediately come to mind for the fields that I’m interested in are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote transparency in science and policy-making&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mentor others and develop strong collaboration skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean into unusual skill sets, as I discuss in &amp;ldquo;Pursuing STEM, Motivated by the Humanities&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, one of the things I appreciate about the core philosophical framework of 80,000 Hours is their emphasis on &lt;strong&gt;moral uncertainty and moderation&lt;/strong&gt;. I believe it is important for all of us to remain intellectually humble and to avoid choosing extreme courses of action unless there is broad consensus on the existence of substantial evidence that the benefits of doing so will outweigh the costs. &lt;em&gt;Note: despite this acknowledgement, most of the EA / 80,000 Hours arguments tend to lean utilitarian.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching goal of exploring these ideas is to develop a framework for thinking about our impact on others that allows us to move forward on an informed path, instead of being paralyzed or moving forward on an ineffective (or even harmful) path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;resources-to-explore&#34;&gt;Resources to Explore&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are so many well-written, in-depth but also accessible resources provided by EA / 80,000 Hours. Here are links to some of the core resources and other articles that have most resonated for me. These in turn link to many other articles, so if these topics interest you, you may find yourself going down a rabbit hole, as I have done many times!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that nearly all of the resources related to high-impact careers are intended for a college-educated audience with the ability to choose / change their career path. However, the resources related to effective donations are relevant for almost everyone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/articles/introduction-to-effective-altruism&#34;&gt;Intro to Effective Altruism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/should-you-wait/&#34;&gt;Should You Wait to Make a Difference?&lt;/a&gt; (donating time or money now versus investing in career capital and/or investing money)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/advanced-series/&#34;&gt;80,000 Hours Key Ideas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/career-guide/making-a-difference/&#34;&gt;Anyone Can Have an Impact&lt;/a&gt; (discussion of charity and volunteering)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/framework/&#34;&gt;Career Framework&lt;/a&gt; (thinking through impact, personal satisfaction, career capital, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/problem-framework/&#34;&gt;Problem Framework&lt;/a&gt; (thinking through scale, solvability, and neglectedness)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/problem-profiles/&#34;&gt;Problem Profiles&lt;/a&gt; (the global issues that 80,000 Hours thinks are currently most pressing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/career-reviews/&#34;&gt;High-Impact Careers&lt;/a&gt; (the careers that 80,000 Hours thinks currently hold the highest potential for impact)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/faqs-criticism-objections&#34;&gt;FAQs and Common Objections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/articles/johannes-ackva-an-update-to-our-thinking-on-climate-change&#34;&gt;EA Applied to Climate Change&lt;/a&gt; (including this because I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in this topic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
