<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Science Policy | Ellen Considine</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/science-policy/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/tags/science-policy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Science Policy</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:4321/media/icon_hu68170e94a17a2a43d6dcb45cf0e8e589_3079_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Science Policy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/science-policy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate &amp; Health Event Series, Science Policy Group</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/project/scipol/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/project/scipol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the roles I undertook as Vice-President of the Harvard graduate student science policy group was co-organizing a series of events at the intersection of climate &amp;amp; health. This brought together students and staff from across the Harvard School of Public Health, Medical School, Dental School, and Graduate School of Arts &amp;amp; Sciences. In particular, I spearheaded and moderated a panel and networking dinner focused on the translation of research into policy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Having an Impact, Part 2</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/impact-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/impact-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Effective Altruism (EA) / 80,000 Hours philosophy has guided many of my thoughts and actions over the past 4+ years. In this post, my goal is to articulate some of the most important and generalizable aspects of my EA journey so far. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet encountered the EA / 80,000 Hours movement, I recommend checking out Part 1!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;overall-reflections&#34;&gt;Overall Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internalizing many of the EA / 80,000 Hours ideas guided me into the field of environmental public health / biostatistics, no question. This semester, I’ve really enjoyed seeing the close alignment between these fields / movements in my introductory public health classes. Of course, there are countless other fields in which one can pursue having a positive impact along the lines of the EA literature. I can simply confirm that I am glad to have made decisions in accordance with this paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, critically examining one&amp;rsquo;s overall impact is not for the faint of heart. Some of the most distressing loops I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten stuck in over the years include questioning whether certain career / life opportunities are worth their associated environmental costs (such as plane flights) and financial costs (i.e. would it be better to donate money now to a cause than to invest in my personal career capital, which may help that or another cause in the long term?), balancing avoidance of the &amp;ldquo;white savior complex&amp;rdquo; with the potential for bringing in funding and technical expertise to under-resourced areas, and deciding how much to focus on science vs. public policy more directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;balancing-different-kinds-of-good&#34;&gt;Balancing Different Kinds of Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crux of the matter is that nothing we can do is 100% good by all definitions. Even determining if our actions have net positive impact is challenging / impossible. Was my flight to Nepal to volunteer with Engineers Without Borders net positive? In addition to the work that we did and the personal connections we made, all of the learning I did over that summer has helped me to build a more resilient mental framework about global inequities and to more realistically compare pathways for reducing global poverty. But will my having that knowledge end up being more helpful to others than if I’d simply donated the money for my plane ticket to one of the most cost-effective charitable organizations? Wouldn’t my environmental footprint be so much smaller if, instead of going to graduate school and pursuing a professional career, I went and lived off the grid in a tiny cabin in the woods? But then I would be reducing my opportunities to interact with and help others&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The what-ifs are endless, and it’s easy to feel overwhelmed if you let yourself dive too deep too often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the &lt;em&gt;timing&lt;/em&gt; of individual giving, I have found &lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/should-you-wait/&#34;&gt;this 80,000 Hours framework&lt;/a&gt; to be helpful. But that still doesn’t necessarily help us distinguish between / balance different types of “good”. Any model that we make to try and quantify and compare different kinds of impacts will have massive uncertainty and subjectivity because there are so many things that are difficult and/or rely on philosophical judgements to quantify. How do we value investment in public K-12 education versus Medicare? Funding to conserve biodiversity versus to fight oppression based on race, gender, or sexual identity? Etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much as I enjoy building mathematical models to describe the world, I don&amp;rsquo;t believe there is a way to maximize good across all the areas of life and society that I care about. Ultimately, on an individual level we have to choose what cause(s) to prioritize based on personal affinity and potential for impact. On a societal level, I believe that democracy is one of our best tools for deciding fair allocation of resources, though even the best national democracy is likely to fall short when considering international and/or intergenerational issues, given lack of representation by all affected parties. This, in turn, highlights the importance of public education, as it can help a population to be aware of the plights of other people across space and time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fighting-the-white--privileged-savior-complex&#34;&gt;Fighting the White / Privileged Savior Complex&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest issues with the traditional EA paradigm is that it often assumes, or at least strongly implies, that people from privileged backgrounds can know and do what’s best for people in under-resourced situations. This can lead to ineffective or even harmful interventions, and also often perpetuates professional and socio-cultural power differentials between people in higher- and lower-income countries or communities within the same country. This problem is acknowledged (with links to more lengthy discussions) in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/faqs-criticism-objections#how-are-the-people-youre-trying-to-help-involved-in-the-decision-making&#34;&gt;Effective Altruism list of common objections&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experiences associated with Engineers Without Borders confronted me with related issues countless times, and in large part convinced me to pursue a career in which I could help gain knowledge and allocate resources on more systemic levels. However, as I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed with multiple professors and other respected mentors, the counterweight is that directly focusing on research or interventions in low-income areas can bring in much-needed funding from higher-income institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue will not disappear any time soon; I anticipate needing to re-evaluate my ability to provide assistance without overstepping in all my future projects. In general, I believe that people with lived experience and/or intimate expertise must be included (and ideally should lead) when making decisions regarding ways to promote causes such as poverty reduction and racial justice. I dive deeper into this last conviction in my &amp;ldquo;Reflections on Privilege in Higher Education&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;careers-in-science-vs-policy&#34;&gt;Careers in Science vs. Policy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is clearly a spectrum in terms of how long it takes our work to positively impact the lives of others. In terms of fields that I’m interested in: many technical problems in science (especially those focused on methodology) are not immediately relevant for helping other people (and thus may feel less impactful) in the way that pushing forward legislation in a government agency or working for a non-governmental organization can be. This can be disheartening for those of us who are motivated by a more personal connection to the impacts of our work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I sense (and have been told by respected mentors) that this is changing somewhat: many scientists are beginning to engage directly with decision makers. This trend is boosted by the increasing availability of near-real-time data sets (e.g. Covid-19 counts) and recognition that sorting through such data sets often requires scientific expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, while I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;ll continue to grapple with such questions for many years to come, I&amp;rsquo;m operating under the hope that by gaining a data science skill set grounded in public health applications, I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to strike a balance in my career between indirect and direct work to help others. Though I’m still very much in the midst of figuring this stuff out, my best advice to stay motivated (for anyone following a similar path) is to seek out opportunities to help others along the way, through mentoring, collaborating on applied projects, volunteering, or some combination of the above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;parting-thoughts&#34;&gt;Parting Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I have found the EA / 80,000 Hours framework to be useful in framing my individual pursuit of positive societal impact, I do not believe that this is the only way to make decisions leading to a meaningful life. For instance, I highly value others&amp;rsquo; decision to pursue careers in music and writing fiction. Art could be considered a different kind of positive impact, but I tend to see it as divergent from the traditional EA / 80,000 Hours path.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Others&#39; Ideas that Resonate</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/project/ideas_resonate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/project/ideas_resonate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are lists of articles, podcasts, videos, etc. that I intend to continuously update as I come across well-explained, powerful ideas that relate directly to my field(s) of interest. For the most part, these resources are more conversational than technical, and are meant to inspire as well as inform. Also see my list of recommended nonfiction books, which spans a larger range of topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;environmental-health&#34;&gt;Environmental Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessing the health burden from air pollution &amp;ndash; Science perspective, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;StoryMap: &amp;ldquo;Air Pollution and Health: The Global Impacts of Fossil Fuels&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; State of Global Air, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaging Socially Vulnerable Communities and Communicating About Climate Change &amp;ndash; NASEM, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leveraging Air Quality Research Advancements to Assess and Address Exposure Inequities &amp;ndash; Goldman, 2023. Environmental Health Perspectives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are “safe” exposure levels really “safe”? &amp;ndash; Program on Reproductive Health and the Environment, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Western lawmakers spot opening in smoke crisis &amp;ndash; Axios, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A conversation on air pollution in the United States &amp;ndash; Nature Geoscience, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naming civic health in environmental justice discourse: The Jackson water crisis &amp;ndash; Nwanaji-Enwerem &amp;amp; Casey, 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flipping the Climate Debate from Costs to Benefits &amp;ndash; Anenberg, 2021. Environmental Health News&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tackling Air Pollution and Climate Justice Together &amp;ndash; Moses &amp;amp; Roy, 2021. Environmental Defense Fund&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Closing the Data Gap: A Cost-Effective Way to Improve [Global] Air Quality &amp;ndash; Hasenkopf, 2021. World Economic Forum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Air Pollution Diminishes Future Generations&amp;rsquo; Economic Opportunities &amp;ndash; Voorheis, 2021. US Census&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Feedback to Improve Accountability in Global Environmental Health and Engineering &amp;ndash; Thomas &amp;amp; Brown, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is AI revolutionizing environmental health? (Simply Statistics &amp;ndash; Peng, 2019). In general, this blog has a lot of cool posts for data scientists and educators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental Health Disparities - An Overview (Harvard Chan NIEHS Center for Environmental Health) &amp;ndash; Mendonça, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ClimateBits: Unhealthy Air &amp;ndash; 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is Environmental Health? &amp;ndash; YouTube, NYU School of Global Public Health, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Podcasts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agents of Change in Environmental Justice &amp;ndash; podcast featuring emerging leaders from historically excluded backgrounds in science and academia who are reimagining solutions for a just and healthy planet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is Your Brain on Pollution &amp;ndash; Freakonomics podcast, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Data Science to Study Air Pollution&amp;rsquo;s Effect on Covid-19 (Women in Data Science podcast) &amp;ndash; Dominici &amp;amp; Nethery, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Atmospheric Tales &amp;ndash; podcast discussing global environmental health, 2020 onwards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decolonizing Air Pollution Science &amp;ndash; deSouza, 2020 / MIT Community Innovators Lab (CoLab) Radio (overall archive). Stories and reflections on the interplay of science and technology with community development and planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feature-length / series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How air pollution impacts our brains, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NASEM Climate Crossroads Summit 2023 (video playlist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NASEM Workshop on Communities, Climate Change, and Health Equity – Lessons Learned in Addressing Inequities in Heat-Related Climate Change Impacts (2023)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HSPH Climate, Health, &amp;amp; Equity Symposium 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Health Effects Institute (HEI) Science on the 7th &amp;ndash; series discussing current critical topics in air quality and global health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearing the Air: Why Now Is the Time to Tackle Global Air Pollution &amp;ndash; HSPH + WHO + CNN, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking the Temperature: Your Health, Our Climate, and What We Can Do About It &amp;ndash; Mazumder, 2021. Harvard Science in the News series.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Story of Plastic (2019). Documentary examining issues and opportunities throughout the lifecycle of plastic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dark Waters (2019). Dramatic recreation of Rob Bilott&amp;rsquo;s case against the chemical manufacturing company DuPont after they contaminated a town with unregulated chemicals. &lt;em&gt;For more information on the environmental health science occurring behind the scenes, check out the C8 Science Panel website.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative on Health and the Environment: Climate Change and Health, 2019. Collection of videos, focusing on the topics of extreme heat, air pollution, extreme weather events, and infectious diseases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Crowd &amp;amp; the Cloud &amp;ndash; Abdalati, 2017. Video series discussing citizen science used in environmental health applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-science--statistics&#34;&gt;Data Science / Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data in Earth science: Emerging practice and promise &amp;ndash; Science review, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Democratizing the future of AI R&amp;amp;D: NSF to launch National AI Research Resource pilot (2024)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What Should Data Science Education Do with Large Language Models? &amp;ndash; Tu et al, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NASA and IBM Openly Release Geospatial AI Foundation Model for NASA Earth Observation Data (2023)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strengthening [global] public health systems through artificial intelligence &amp;ndash; HSPH, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvard Graduate Transforms High School Math Curriculum: Skew The Script, a nonprofit organization, provides free, socially-relevant math + statistics lessons to high school teachers across the country &amp;ndash; Harvard Data Science Initiative, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple Women’s Health Study advances understanding of menstrual cycles and health (2023) &amp;ndash;Example of thoughtful data collection generating insights that are highly relevant for both clinicians and policy makers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there a role for statistics in artificial intelligence? &amp;ndash; Friedrich et al, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the Most Important Statistical Ideas of the Past 50 Years? &amp;ndash; Gelman &amp;amp; Vehtari, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Artificial Intelligence&amp;rsquo;s Promise &amp;amp; Peril (2021) &amp;ndash; Harvard School of Public Health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter thread: best data visualizations (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What Are the Values of Data, Data Science, or Data Scientists? &amp;ndash; Meng, 2021. Harvard Data Science Review editorial piece.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistics Monitors the Environment and Statistics Informs Health Policy &amp;ndash; ASA Statistical Significance Series&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ASCCR Frame for Learning Essential Collaboration Skills &amp;ndash; Vance &amp;amp; Smith, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Career of Gertrude M. Cox &amp;ndash; NC State Library&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Podcasts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mental Health Challenges: How Can Data Science Help? &amp;ndash; Harvard Data Science Review Podcast, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Casual Inference podcast by Ellie Murray and Lucy D&amp;rsquo;Agostino McGowan, specifically this episode featuring Roger Peng: &amp;ldquo;Why Everyone is Excited About Causal Inference These Days&amp;rdquo; (2020)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feature-length / series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shaping the Future of AI &amp;ndash; National Academies; one insightful discussion can be found in the &amp;ldquo;Navigating Ethical Dilemmas&amp;rdquo; section in this article&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop Explaining Black Box Machine Learning Models for High Stakes Decisions and Use Interpretable Models Instead (Harvard Data Science Initiative Bias^2 seminar) &amp;ndash; Rudin, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;career--miscellaneous&#34;&gt;Career / Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Human Implications of AI with Brian Christian &amp;ndash; NASEM, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time to support Indigenous science &amp;ndash; Wall Kimmerer &amp;amp; Artelle, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are you saving the world? &amp;ndash; Parast, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the evidence-based advice we found on how to be more successful in any job &amp;ndash; Todd (80,000 Hours), 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Field-Specific Ability Beliefs as an Explanation for Gender Differences in Academics’ Career Trajectories: Evidence From Public Profiles on ORCID.org &amp;ndash; Hannak et al, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing Women’s Representation in STEM Fields &amp;ndash; Gray, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which food is better for the planet? &amp;ndash; Washington Post Climate Lab (2023). Interactive visualizations comparing different food types over various environmental dimensions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A list of the most high-impact, evidence-based organizations fighting climate change &amp;ndash; Samuel, 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rethinking international development strategy—and hearing echoes of global challenges in the United States &amp;ndash; Harvard Kennedy School faculty, 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impostors Anonymous &amp;ndash; Witten, 2022. Helpful thoughts on impostor syndrome in academia / high-achievement communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My experience with imposter syndrome—and how to (partly) overcome it &amp;ndash; Rodriguez (80,000 Hours), 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Americans experience a false social reality by underestimating popular climate policy support by nearly half &amp;ndash; Sparkman, Geiger, &amp;amp; Weber, 2022.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In academia, we need two types of researchers: divers and surfers &amp;ndash; Pandya, 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Putting Mental Health in America on the Map &amp;ndash; Geraghty (ESRI), 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Public Health Took Part in Its Own Downfall &amp;ndash; The Atlantic, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effective Altruism: An Update to Our Thinking On Climate Change &amp;ndash; Ackva, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Five Ways To Prioritize Better &amp;ndash; Bye, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200 Years in 4 Minutes &amp;ndash; Rosling, 2017. Global relationships between lifespan and income over time, across countries. Note: there are many videos of Rosling presenting other cool data visualizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Podcasts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Degrees of Freedom &amp;ndash; Hasenkopf, 2020. Exploring many different ways that scientists can have positive impact through their careers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AAAS STPF Sci on the Fly. A variety of science and policy topics, written by scientists working in the federal government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feature-length / series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvard School of Public Health YouTube Channel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science x Policy Crossroads: Pathways toward Health Policy &amp;ndash; ten people&amp;rsquo;s stories illustrating different careers at the intersection of science and policy, put together by the National Science Policy Network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AAAS Voices: Countering Science Misinformation (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
