<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Career Advice | Ellen Considine</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/career-advice/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/tags/career-advice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Career Advice</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:4321/media/icon_hu68170e94a17a2a43d6dcb45cf0e8e589_3079_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Career Advice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/career-advice/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Having an Impact, Part 1</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/impact-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/impact-part1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My views and aspirations for both my professional and my personal life have been profoundly influenced by the Effective Altruism (EA) / 80,000 Hours movement. This post is meant to introduce those who haven’t encountered this movement to it. See &amp;ldquo;On Having an Impact, Part 2&amp;rdquo; for some of my reflections in light of this overarching philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;intro-to-effective-altruism-and-80000-hours&#34;&gt;Intro to Effective Altruism and 80,000 Hours&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Instead of citing everything in the paragraphs below, I’m including a list of links at the end of this post, which I encourage you to explore!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core question of EA / 80,000 Hours is: &lt;strong&gt;how can I most effectively help other people, given finite resources?&lt;/strong&gt; There are many ways in which we can help others: directly and indirectly, material and non-material goods and services, in the short-term and in the long-term, concentrated and dispersed across individuals…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80,000 Hours often highlights the impact you can have in your career, but EA also encompasses the impact you can have by giving money to organizations which are doing good, engaging in advocacy, or helping others to increase their impact. Some of the key ideas promoted by EA / 80,000 Hours include focusing on cost-effectiveness, long-termism, personal fit, and collaboration with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost-effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt; means optimization of positive impact per dollar spent. To motivate this: it has been shown that the best global health interventions can be orders of magnitude more cost-effective than others. Thankfully, there are now organizations whose purpose is to determine the cost-effectiveness of different charitable organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EA / 80,000 Hours also argues that if we factor in the wellbeing of future generations, then &lt;strong&gt;long-term impacts&lt;/strong&gt; become more and more favorable. In terms of high-impact careers, this often translates into research- or policy-based vocations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding &lt;strong&gt;personal fit&lt;/strong&gt;, 80,000 hours makes a pretty strong case that we are most effective in jobs that align with our skills, interests, and personalities. However, they also discuss how individual abilities are most often built, not innate, so we can guide ourselves in certain directions over time if so we choose. While figuring out what kind(s) of work to pursue, they advocate “cheap” tests such as reaching out to others and trying things out on small scales. College is a great time to do this, as I discuss in &amp;ldquo;The Power of Showing Up and Reaching Out&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration&lt;/strong&gt; is crucial for addressing large-scale and/or complex problems. Although collaboration has not always been promoted as a core idea by the EA/80,000 Hours community, I am highlighting it here because of my personal belief in its importance. Some conclusions that stuck out to me from &lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/coordination/&#34;&gt;80,000 Hours’ article about collaboration&lt;/a&gt; are that to maximize coordination within a shared-aims community, we should:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prioritize upholding norms of kindness and honesty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invest in community capital&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be willing to specialize, explore, and even take opportunities with worse personal fit if they play to our comparative advantages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though there are many directions to take the above list of ideas, some actions that immediately come to mind for the fields that I’m interested in are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote transparency in science and policy-making&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mentor others and develop strong collaboration skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean into unusual skill sets, as I discuss in &amp;ldquo;Pursuing STEM, Motivated by the Humanities&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, one of the things I appreciate about the core philosophical framework of 80,000 Hours is their emphasis on &lt;strong&gt;moral uncertainty and moderation&lt;/strong&gt;. I believe it is important for all of us to remain intellectually humble and to avoid choosing extreme courses of action unless there is broad consensus on the existence of substantial evidence that the benefits of doing so will outweigh the costs. &lt;em&gt;Note: despite this acknowledgement, most of the EA / 80,000 Hours arguments tend to lean utilitarian.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching goal of exploring these ideas is to develop a framework for thinking about our impact on others that allows us to move forward on an informed path, instead of being paralyzed or moving forward on an ineffective (or even harmful) path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;resources-to-explore&#34;&gt;Resources to Explore&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are so many well-written, in-depth but also accessible resources provided by EA / 80,000 Hours. Here are links to some of the core resources and other articles that have most resonated for me. These in turn link to many other articles, so if these topics interest you, you may find yourself going down a rabbit hole, as I have done many times!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that nearly all of the resources related to high-impact careers are intended for a college-educated audience with the ability to choose / change their career path. However, the resources related to effective donations are relevant for almost everyone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/articles/introduction-to-effective-altruism&#34;&gt;Intro to Effective Altruism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/should-you-wait/&#34;&gt;Should You Wait to Make a Difference?&lt;/a&gt; (donating time or money now versus investing in career capital and/or investing money)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/advanced-series/&#34;&gt;80,000 Hours Key Ideas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/career-guide/making-a-difference/&#34;&gt;Anyone Can Have an Impact&lt;/a&gt; (discussion of charity and volunteering)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/framework/&#34;&gt;Career Framework&lt;/a&gt; (thinking through impact, personal satisfaction, career capital, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/articles/problem-framework/&#34;&gt;Problem Framework&lt;/a&gt; (thinking through scale, solvability, and neglectedness)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/problem-profiles/&#34;&gt;Problem Profiles&lt;/a&gt; (the global issues that 80,000 Hours thinks are currently most pressing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://80000hours.org/career-reviews/&#34;&gt;High-Impact Careers&lt;/a&gt; (the careers that 80,000 Hours thinks currently hold the highest potential for impact)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/faqs-criticism-objections&#34;&gt;FAQs and Common Objections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/articles/johannes-ackva-an-update-to-our-thinking-on-climate-change&#34;&gt;EA Applied to Climate Change&lt;/a&gt; (including this because I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in this topic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pursuing STEM, Motivated by the Humanities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/stem-humanities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/stem-humanities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In an alternate but closely related universe, I could easily have chosen a career in the humanities. I love learning about sociology and philosophy. I am most intellectually enthusiastic when pondering underlying societal phenomenon and the ways we might go about addressing societal issues which manifest human suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, several important factors guided my path into statistics and data science. Firstly, my parents brought my brother and me up to be very conscious of the vocational value of our educations, as well as to gravitate towards career paths which keep doors open and allow for maximal flexibility. Given the modern world&amp;rsquo;s number and variety of jobs in STEM, we were both nudged in that direction. Under the umbrella of practicality, I also grew up with the knowledge that PhDs in STEM are most often fully funded, while many/most other graduate degrees are not, and that it is most often easier to transition from a more technical / hard science field into a less technical / softer skills position than to transition the other way. Further, the fact that both of my parents studied science and math made going into STEM the obvious thing to do. Somewhere along the way, I also came to realize that being someone who wanted to and was able to effectively bridge ideas between STEM and humanities disciplines was relatively rare, making this a valuable niche to pursue. Finally, as I discuss at the end of &amp;ldquo;The Benefits of Attending Your State’s Public University for Undergrad&amp;rdquo;, there were a number of factors at CU that kept me in STEM once I was there, namely stronger peers and harder classes (on average) and more research opportunities &amp;ndash; many professors need students who can assist with quantitative tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I reflect on my experiences as a STEM student with a humanities heart. A recent conversation with an older student in my PhD program reminded me that I&amp;rsquo;m far from alone in this and that being candid about our experiences can help to assure and guide others as they make their way on similar trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-strength-of-interdisciplinarity&#34;&gt;The Strength of Interdisciplinarity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout undergrad, my choices of classes, projects, and extracurricular activities  were guided by my humanities interests. And it was at the intersection of my STEM and socially-oriented studies that my most interesting and meaningful experiences arose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many of my upper division classes, I had the opportunity to design a final project that built off of material from the class. Being able to select a social or environmental application that I was interested in made doing all of these projects more fun and useful. For instance: in my machine learning class, I worked on a model to classify cervical cancer cases (a huge public health problem in low- and middle-income countries). That same semester, I chose to write my final paper for my health and medical geography class on cervical cancer.  In my advanced remote sensing course, I analyzed air pollution trends (captured by satellite proxy) over six capital cities in South Asia. In my data assimilation class, I modeled annual flu seasons in Colorado. In my network dynamics course, I developed a model that used Census data to predict migration of people between major cities in the US. In my development geography class, I wrote a paper on the incorporation of data science into global public health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This combination of STEM and social interests also led me to opportunities outside of classes. For instance, my simultaneous enrollment in environmental sociology and introductory data science courses in my freshman year led me to my environmental health data science research internship of the next three years (see &amp;ldquo;The Power of Showing Up and Reaching Out&amp;rdquo;). Drawing on my interests and affinities for mathematical modeling, analyzing social and environmental issues, and writing helped my team do well in the international COMAP MCM/ICM (see &amp;ldquo;Advice for the COMAP MCM/ICM&amp;rdquo;). And my interest in using STEM to help reduce socioeconomic inequities led me to CU Engineers Without Borders (EWB). My involvement in EWB over the four years was one of the most educational and meaningful experiences of my time in college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, being grounded by a sense of societal purpose helped me both internally and externally. Internally: feeling like I was doing meaningful work and/or tangibly preparing for a career of meaningful work helped motivate me when the going got tough. Externally: having a framework on which to base my personal narrative and goals made it much easier to apply for opportunities such as scholarships and graduate school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that developing this framework, figuring out how to combine my interests, was straightforward. For a detailed account of the twists and turns of my experience, see my post &amp;ldquo;On Finding a Career Path&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;potent-challenges&#34;&gt;Potent Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous sections might have made this kind of path seem like a no-brainer. However, the most obvious downside of my path is that I have struggled a lot with some of my applied math courses. Countless times, material in the more theory-based courses has made me feel intimidated and inadequate. I know from conversations with other students in my undergrad and grad programs that impostor syndrome (feeling like you don&amp;rsquo;t belong) is quite common. However, I suspect that I might have felt / continue to feel less anxious about my intellectual abilities had I chosen a field for which my brain feels a more direct affinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, being in a STEM program can make it harder to develop soft skills, due to lack of time. Taking the minimum required humanities classes for a STEM degree may not provide you with your desired levels of skill in writing, oral presentation/discussion, or thinking critically about social issues. Thus, you have to consciously carve out time for learning and practicing in these areas if you want them in your interdisciplinary toolbox. Especially when you have many other commitments, carving out extra time may not be trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;parting-thoughts&#34;&gt;Parting Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself in a similar position on your education/career path, I recommend going out of your way to find opportunities to use your interdisciplinary skills. These experiences can help to validate your efforts and make bearable the parts you don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy as much. To manage the impostor syndrome, I&amp;rsquo;ve also found it helpful to remind myself that I&amp;rsquo;m not directly competing (in a broader career sense) with the people who are killing the math theory game. If you&amp;rsquo;re someone who can use STEM tools but who are also driven by and can draw on non-technical domain knowledge, you&amp;rsquo;re able to define your own playing field, or league. Lastly, I advise carving out time to develop strong communication skills (written and oral). Collaborating across disciplines, especially if you want your work to have broader impacts, requires effective communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A related article (not mine): &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/XvN2QQpKTuEzgkZHY/being-the-pareto-best-in-the-world&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Being the (Pareto) Best in the World&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Finding a Career Path</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/finding-career-path/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/finding-career-path/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Planning out your life is impossible. Circumstances change, people change. New information comes to your attention and you shift course. But at the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s helpful to have a sense of direction, a sense of purpose, to guide your thoughts and actions. Having an idea of where you want to end up can provide this sense of direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think of navigating life in this way like hiking through the wilderness. Setting your sights on a distant mountain frees you from having to expend energy on wayfinding every second of every day. You can focus instead on where you&amp;rsquo;re putting your feet and on enjoying the more nearby scenery. As you&amp;rsquo;re making your way across the plains, a different mountain might come into view. Or, maybe, the coast of a large body of water. You might decide this new destination looks better than the first mountain, so you re-orient in that direction. Maybe you&amp;rsquo;ll visit the first mountain someday, maybe you won&amp;rsquo;t. And so it goes: at any point in time, you are hiking towards something, but that something can change as frequently as you want it to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuing with this analogy: as you make your way in your intended direction, you will likely encounter other people (depending on how remote the trail is). If you are able to describe where you&amp;rsquo;re headed, these people may be able to give you advice, having previously explored similar places. This is another reason it&amp;rsquo;s helpful to have a sense of direction: you can make it easier for other people to help you. The more detail you provide, the more specific other people can be with their advice. And, if you&amp;rsquo;re visibly inspired about where you&amp;rsquo;re going, other people are often more inspired to help you get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, maybe somewhere along your path, you see a sign post indicating that there is a town a few miles away. If you have a sense of where you&amp;rsquo;re attempting to go in the near future, then you might choose to go stock up on appropriate supplies: if you&amp;rsquo;re headed up the mountain, you might get some gloves. If you&amp;rsquo;re headed to the coast, you might get some sunblock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally have found the advice &amp;ldquo;always be moving forward on a path, even if you&amp;rsquo;re often switching paths&amp;rdquo; to be very helpful so far in my education and life. I have also frequently used the strategies of asking others for advice along the way and stocking up on various forms of domain knowledge and technical skills if I can foresee a major use for them farther on my intended path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next two sections, I share the relatively abbreviated story of how I ended up with a major in applied math, minors in statistics, economics, and geography, and an upcoming five more years of school in environmental biostatistics. The first section is the more straightforward narrative that I might share in an interview or application. The second section is the more nuanced, more human, and likely more relatable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;alls-clear-in-hindsight-one-version-of-how-i-ended-up-on-my-current-path&#34;&gt;All&amp;rsquo;s clear in hindsight: one version of how I ended up on my current path&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early high school, the societal issue that I cared about the most was environmental sustainability. In my junior year of high school, I took an environmental systems class that illustrated the close relationship between environmental and economic issues. My family also talked fairly regularly about the issue of economic inequality in our society. When I started college, I decided to study applied math with an emphasis / minor in economics and potentially also one in environmental science. The applied math major appealed to me because it would give me some concrete problem-solving skills while also allowing me to explore other areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my freshman year, getting involved with Engineers Without Borders and reading outside of classes helped me to see more connections between economic development, environmental issues, and equity, as well as to recognize that if I want to help large numbers of people in the US and abroad, my background and skill set are well-suited to working at a systemic level: influencing policy and directing resources to where they&amp;rsquo;re most needed on a large scale. (For more thoughts in this vein, see &amp;ldquo;On Having an Impact, Part 2&amp;rdquo;.) I also self-confirmed my affinity for data science through an introductory data science course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my sophomore year, I began working as a data science intern on the environmental health team in Earth Lab (see &amp;ldquo;The Power of Showing Up and Reaching Out&amp;rdquo; for the story of how I got involved in this research). Through being in Earth Lab, I learned that it is possible to harness large, publicly-available data sets to answer all kinds of environmental questions. This inspired me to take some classes in remote sensing and geographic information systems (GIS) in the department of geography. Finally, the specific research that I was doing on the environmental health team (helping to investigate statistical associations between air pollution from wildfires and human health outcomes) inspired me to learn more about public health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fall of my junior year, I took a health and medical geography class taught by Colleen, my research mentor. This course confirmed in my mind that public health lies at the intersection of economics, the environment, and human well-being. I began talking with professors about pursuing a graduate degree in public health that utilized data science tools, and stumbled upon the field of biostatistics. In the spring of my junior year, I had the chance to take classes in general statistical modeling and spatial statistics. My enjoyment of both of these classes confirmed to me that biostatistics with an emphasis on environmental health (which often uses spatial statistics) would be a good fit for me in graduate school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer between my junior and senior years, I spent a lot of time reading scientific papers about air pollution epidemiology and childhood asthma to complement our collaboration project with the Denver Department of Public Health &amp;amp; Environment (again, see &amp;ldquo;The Power of Showing Up and Reaching Out&amp;rdquo;). This helped me gain familiarity with some environmental health methods as well as with what is generally known about the health impacts of various environmental exposures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my senior year, having chosen the path that I wanted to take in graduate school, I spent some more time exploring. In addition to my technical applied math and statistics courses, I took a graduate-level development geography course to gain a more academic perspective on the history and current theory on international development work, a course on statistical collaboration which taught students how to communicate and work effectively with domain experts so as to provide statistical expertise on various projects, and a philosophy course. These were the most purely enjoyable classes I took all year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, all of my exploration has helped me to identify a discipline that combines many of my interests and will allow me to develop a sufficiently general toolbox of statistical skills that I will be able to continue working on a variety of projects over the course of my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;twists-turns-and-opportunity-costs-another-version-of-my-story&#34;&gt;Twists, turns, and opportunity costs: another version of my story&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The section above might make it seem like I knew what I was doing at every step of the way. During most of my years at CU, however, I felt like I was leaping between career paths: economist, international development expert, GIS scientist, environmental epidemiologist, biostatistician. And there were many more divergent career paths that I considered but did not spend as much time exploring, in part because of my motivation to stay in STEM (see &amp;ldquo;Pursuing STEM, Motivated by the Humanities&amp;rdquo;). In terms of courses: at various points along the way, I envisioned getting minors in computer science, journalism, sociology, or philosophy. I also certainly experienced (and continue to experience) plenty of decision paralysis and impostor syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, my story would not be complete without mentioning that in between my junior and senior years of high school, I had decided to pursue a career in classical music performance, and spent much of my senior year of high school preparing for and carrying out auditions for college programs in music. One of the reasons I originally chose to study applied math at CU was that it seemed like a relatively flexible double-major alongside a major in clarinet performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing about my journey in this way also obscures the opportunity costs of my decisions: there were many experiences, both professional and personal, that some peers had but I did not have in college. For instance: I have zero experience working in the private sector. Many of my friends have learned lots from doing internships at companies over the summer or during the academic year, and I did not explore this avenue. In the personal realm: I spent less time on social and outdoor activities than I might have otherwise enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;overall-thoughts&#34;&gt;Overall thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each of us, I believe that there are many ways to lead a fulfilling life. I suspect that I could just as easily have fallen onto a different career path and felt just as fulfilled had my opportunities and mentorship been different. That said, given the opportunities and mentorship that life does present us with, how can we go about choosing a path to follow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found an iterative process to work the best. Start out on one path (maybe one that will give you a general set of skills), then, if something comes along that looks interesting, check out that for a while to see how it feels. This might sound completely random, but if we simultaneously spend time figuring out what we really value in our lives and work, then I believe that the paths that appear and look appealing will tend to be at least somewhat complementary to the one we&amp;rsquo;re already on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing to remember is that, especially in an era where many (if not most) people have more than one job during their career, switching gears and changing paths is not a bad thing. Each time you re-orient, you will likely retain what you gained in your previous orientation. And in the end, having a more unusual path can often provide you with a less common and more compelling skillset.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Honest Conversation About Box-Checking</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/box-checking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/box-checking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Box-checking&amp;rdquo; has a pretty negative connotation. It implies that your actions are inauthentic: the only reason you are doing something is to put it on your resume / achieve some glamorous end goal, not because you actually want to do it. It is often associated with helicopter parents and overachieving students trying to get into prestigious colleges. It is perceived as soulless running of the rat race. In this post, I attempt to flesh out a more nuanced perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I have observed that feeling the need to fill out one&amp;rsquo;s resume and appear objectively impressive can be incredibly stressful and potentially damaging for individuals&amp;rsquo; mental health. In high school, many of my peers were stressed all the time about whether they were doing enough to be accepted into their dream colleges. I feel fortunate to have avoided this in my late teenage years because I planned to attend my home state university. I truly believe that I was doing the things I did in high school (focusing mostly on music and sports) because I enjoyed them, not because I felt forced to do them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After starting college, however, the lines between authentic engagement and box-checking became more blurred for me. Did I join Engineers Without Borders purely because I wanted to help other people and learn about the world or because I wanted this cool international volunteering experience in my back pocket? Did I start doing my research internship because I really wanted to spend more hours of the day learning how to code in R or because I knew that it would open doors to future opportunities? Did I spend more time than I needed to setting up a socially-positive collaborative research project simply because I thought that it was important work to do or because I was already planning to apply for grad school in public health and knew that such a project would help strengthen my application? The honest answer to all of these questions is &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt;. At times, I have felt uncomfortable with this duality: am I doing this because I care about it or because it will look good on my resume?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I have come to the conclusion that this is a false duality. The overarching question to be asking is whether or not my actions are aligned with my values. If my career goals are aligned with my values, then doing things that help to advance my career (including working harder than I might otherwise enjoy) are often consistent, especially if I find the things I&amp;rsquo;m doing along the way to be meaningful in their own right. However, how can I determine the makeup of my intentions? How can I recognize whether I am motivated more by the prestige of an accomplishment or by the opportunities to help other people that will open up if I have that accomplishment? Does this balance of intentions (which is likely dynamic) even matter if the outcomes are positive for society? Thoughts in this vein are explored more in &amp;ldquo;On Having an Impact, Part 2&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking a step back: the truth is, to have any semblance of control over your life, I believe you have to be at least somewhat strategic. One of my favorite professors likes to say that being successful in college (and in life) amounts to making a large number of small-scale good decisions. I add that while many small-scale decisions may be good on their own, one needs a sense of direction or purpose in order for the small decisions to amount to something good on the large scale. In other words, good decision-making requires context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we would all agree that &lt;em&gt;intentionality&lt;/em&gt; is a good thing. Identifying what you value, developing a vision of what you want your life to look like, and taking action to bring your vision about is necessary to avoid floating and letting circumstance and other people&amp;rsquo;s choices dictate what happens to you. Streamlining your efforts towards your goals is often helpful. (See &amp;ldquo;On Finding a Career Path&amp;rdquo;.) But there is also a limit beyond which thinking about the future and attempting to optimize your actions in the name of your goals becomes unhealthy and unhelpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late in my junior year of college, I unintentionally crossed this boundary. I have always been someone who is very aware of the future, but I think what finally tipped me over the edge was that I had spent much of the year up to that point applying for prestigious national scholarships: the Goldwater, the Astronaut, and the Truman scholarships. I had spent so much time writing and editing essays and my CV that I began to lose track of who I was beyond these measures of academic success. Applying for prestigious opportunities became so ingrained in my routine that I was halfway into a preliminary application for the Rhodes Scholarship (a fellowship in the UK) before I realized that I actually wanted to stay in the US for grad school. That summer, after learning that I had been named a Goldwater scholar, an Astronaut scholar, and a winner of the MCM (an international mathematical modeling competition), I felt more anxious and depressed than I ever had before in my life. I convinced myself that I was stressed about big problems in the world, such as climate change, economic inequity, and politics. This rationalization was partially true: I am deeply concerned about these issues and I plan to help work on addressing them for the rest of my life. However, in retrospect, the primary reason for my unhappiness was that I was simultaneously revved and burnt out. I had eyes only for the next sign post, the next box to check to keep optimizing my resume. And I was miserable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, my parents helped me to recognize my obsession and to work on maintaining a healthier mindset and stress level. I now know that managing my tendency to get caught up in the CV game (or any other life &amp;ldquo;competition&amp;rdquo;) will be an ongoing personal challenge. And I know that I am not alone. In today&amp;rsquo;s world, we are constantly presented with snapshots of other people&amp;rsquo;s successes. I call this the social media effect. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s on Facebook or Instagram or LinkedIn, we are constantly shown what other people are most proud of and tend to fixate on the things others have that we do not. People in past generations have certainly experienced this as well, but the internet amplifies it to the extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to my story: despite the unpleasantness of my peak resume obsession, all the time that I had spent reflecting, figuring out what I wanted to work on in the future, and practicing articulating these ideas within the confines of strict word limits was a boon when it came time to apply for grad school. It certainly made my senior year of college a lot less stressful. However, looking back, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure whether I&amp;rsquo;d advise a younger me to follow in my footsteps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where does this jumble of thoughts leave us?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The questions of what to work on and how hard to work are difficult enough without simultaneously questioning our intentions. However, I have come to believe that &lt;em&gt;pausing&lt;/em&gt; and asking ourselves the following every so often can help us to stay on more healthy, grounded paths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Am I feeling fulfilled by the work I am doing?&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes, fulfillment is synonymous with enjoyment. Other times, I might believe the work I&amp;rsquo;m doing is meaningful but not necessarily love completing the day-to-day tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why am I doing this work?&lt;/strong&gt; How do I feel about the balance of inwards (e.g. professional development) versus outwards (e.g. helping others) effort?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are the sacrifices I&amp;rsquo;m making to do this work consistent with my values?&lt;/strong&gt; Sacrifices might be intellectual, monetary, or related to work-life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, no one else can give us these answers. This conclusion may be unsatisfying, but it is up to each of us to decide what we care about and whether our actions (including how hard we&amp;rsquo;re working and how long we have to wait for gratification) are in alignment with what we care about. Honestly answering these questions and willingly making changes in our behavior if and when we identify inconsistencies is a challenging and often cyclic endeavor, but ultimately is necessary if we wish to live authentic and meaningful lives.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Benefits of Attending Your State’s Public University for Undergrad</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/public-university-undergrad/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/public-university-undergrad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I grew up in Boulder, Colorado. The University of Colorado (CU) sits right in the middle of town. To many of my high school peers and their families, attending CU was a fallback. It was seen as unadventurous and not at all prestigious. Despite the many good reasons I had for attending CU, I recognize that these perceptions weighed on me somewhat over the last four years. Now, two months into a PhD program at Harvard, my last subconscious traces of insecurity about my undergraduate education have finally faded. The semester is still ramping up, but I feel very well prepared for success in my classes and research projects. I write this with the hope that others in similar positions in high school will feel more confident than I did in choosing what&amp;rsquo;s right for them and not caring what anyone else thinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, here are the four main reasons for strong students to consider attending their state universities for undergrad: lower cost, lower stress, more opportunities per capita, and connections in your home state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;cost of college&lt;/strong&gt; nowadays is insane. For almost any family, paying between $30,000 and $300,000 for a four-year degree per kid is going to be difficult, if not impossible. If you can get a sufficiently large fraction covered by financial aid or merit scholarships, great. If not, these amounts of money have extremely high opportunity costs. The way my parents described opportunity cost to my brother and me was by telling us how much they had saved for each of us and asking us whether we&amp;rsquo;d like to spend all the money on college-related expenses or save some of it and put that towards other things such as a graduate or professional degree, a down-payment on a place to live, or traveling. This perspective made the financial choice much more tangible, and motivated both my brother and me to go to college in-state. However, I think that many families do not discuss family resources and choice of higher education in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it&amp;rsquo;s a question of taking on debt to pay for a more expensive education, then the choice is even more stark. In addition to hearing about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/06/12/how-student-debt-became-a-1point6-trillion-crisis.html&#34;&gt;college debt crisis&lt;/a&gt; on the news, this fact was driven home for me the year before I started college when my dad helped me make a realistic model of the long-term economic outcomes of college choice in Excel. Between paying off debt (with interest) and losing the opportunity to invest savings early on in life, the total cost of college debt can be enormous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that I imagine few families discuss is the &lt;strong&gt;large number of opportunities per strong student&lt;/strong&gt; at a large state university. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re interested in gaining leadership or research experience, there are often more open resources and faculty members to engage with than there would be at a school where everyone is constantly jockeying for spots in clubs, teams, and research labs. During my time at CU, I observed that highly motivated undergrads (who took initiative in reaching out to professors) were able to gain research experience on par with the graduate students. This may also be true at more prestigious universities, but I think it is much less common and more competitive because the professors already have plenty of highly-qualified grad students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly suspect that I personally would not have been able to maintain good grades, work continuously as a research assistant, and engage in volunteering activities at the level I did at CU had I attended a more elite university. In addition to having less opportunities, I believe that attending a more competitive school would have prevented engagement in this volume of commitments by raising my stress level and inducing burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even at CU, &lt;strong&gt;finding an optimal stress level&lt;/strong&gt; for myself was not easy.  What seems like a fine amount of activities at one point in the semester can very easily feel like too much at other times in the semester (around exams, when a club has a large paperwork deadline, etc.). Another major challenge for me has been building confidence in my technical skills and fighting &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apa.org/gradpsych/2013/11/fraud&#34;&gt;impostor syndrome&lt;/a&gt;. Perceptions abound that math and computer science are difficult, that one must be &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; to do well in these fields. My personal experience over the last four years was that I have had to work very hard to do well in technical courses, but that with enough time, I can learn pretty much any material. This all might sound obvious, but truly internalizing a &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2016/01/what-having-a-growth-mindset-actually-means&#34;&gt;growth mindset&lt;/a&gt; is often quite challenging. I imagine that being in a more competitive academic environment would have made it even harder for me to feel competent, possibly to the point that I would have decided to pursue a less technical degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A side note about academic competition:&lt;/em&gt; a motto of the CU Engineering Honors Program, a residential-academic program that was one of the defining elements of my undergraduate experience, was &amp;ldquo;being ambitious without being competitive&amp;rdquo;. While this is of course easier to say than to do, I believe that it is possible to be a content and successful student with this mindset, especially if academic programs incentivize collaboration. For instance: in my current graduate program, our class grades are not curved, and it is encouraged that we study together and help each other to pass the qualifying exams (comprehensive exams we take after the first year, as a gateway to becoming full-fledged PhD candidates). Being encouraged and supported in maintaining a collaborative mindset in undergrad prepared me well for this environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have found it meaningful to be able to pursue &lt;strong&gt;connections in my home state&lt;/strong&gt;. Whether volunteering for or collaborating with organizations that are based locally or networking with local professionals inside and outside of academia, I have found this personally fulfilling and professionally promising. My perspective is of course biased because I love Colorado and would someday like the choice to be able to move back and be close to my family and the mountains, but I suspect that many young people might be coming to similar conclusions about the appeal of having geographical roots. Especially when considering the financial and environmental costs of travel, choosing to live in a place that fulfills your needs and wants is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One perception I have not yet addressed is that attending one&amp;rsquo;s state school is unadventurous. However, I found that to be a non-issue in my time at CU, despite having grown up less than 3 miles from the university campus. In fact, I suspect that by getting involved with Engineers Without Borders, I learned more about the world than many of my high school peers who went to university in other states. In general, making an effort to get to know lots of different people, taking classes and intellectually engaging in areas which challenged many of my views, and trying out new activities (such as swing and salsa dancing and rock climbing) made my time at college feel plenty adventurous. This might sound cliché, but I tend to think that wherever you end up, there are ways to make life novel if you have an open mindset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Of course, all of us tend to rationalize the choices we have made&lt;/em&gt;. Despite having no regrets about my choices of undergraduate education, I recognize that attending CU drove me (and many of my peers) into STEM more strongly than we might have been driven at more elite colleges. One reason for this is that STEM classes at state schools are often more comparable with those at more prestigious schools than are humanities classes, which causes and is in turn caused by students with stronger academic backgrounds gravitating into STEM degree programs. Another reason for this is that in certain fields such as consulting and law, prestige of your undergraduate institution matters, whereas in STEM (and some other fields), the institution at which you got your terminal degree tends to be the only one that matters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Showing Up and Reaching Out</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/showing-up-reaching-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/showing-up-reaching-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When people ask me for advice about college, this is the number one thing I tell them: you never know what will happen if you show up to an event and/or reach out to someone. I feel very grateful that my parents instilled this in me before I went off to college, because it led to every single one of the best opportunities I had during undergrad. By sharing the following stories, it is my intention that others might be inspired to muster the energy and overcome the initial awkwardness of showing up and reaching out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;story-1-how-i-got-involved-in-undergraduate-research&#34;&gt;Story #1: How I Got Involved in Undergraduate Research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spring of my freshman year of college, two of my courses were an introductory data science course and an environmental sociology course. In the environmental sociology course, there was a brief lecture on the health impacts of air pollution, which I found fascinating. In the data science course, our final project was to analyze a data set of our choice. I thought it would be cool to combine these interests, and after reading a bit online, I came up with the idea of analyzing whether proximity to highways was associated with asthma rates. I spent a while looking for data online and found some aggregated data sets, but thought there were probably much better publicly-available options that I just wasn&amp;rsquo;t finding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I started Googling professors at CU who might know where to get data related to air pollution from roadways. I ended up emailing a professor in environmental engineering who does a lot of work on air pollution. She forwarded me to a professor in geography with expertise in the health impacts of air pollution. This professor, Colleen Reid, invited me to meet with her to discuss my project. Our discussion ended up covering a lot more than just this project, as I learned about her research and other opportunities at CU for applying quantitative methods to study social issues. After our meeting, I sent her an email thanking her for our conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four months later, Colleen emailed me a flyer for an undergraduate data science internship (advised by her) helping to study the health impacts of air pollution from wildfires. It turned out that only two undergraduates applied: me and a student with no background in statistics or data science. Colleen became my research mentor, and I spent the next three years working with her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;story-2-how-i-started-a-collaboration-with-the-denver-department-of-public-health--environment&#34;&gt;Story #2: How I Started A Collaboration with the Denver Department of Public Health &amp;amp; Environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a year and a half after I started working with Colleen, she mentioned to me and her post-doc Melissa that there was going to be a day-long symposium on climate change and health in Denver the following month. We decided to go, even though it meant that I would be skipping a day of school. During one of the presentations, someone mentioned an initiative deploying low-cost air quality sensors at schools in Denver. I was curious to learn more about that initiative, so I made myself a note and started Googling when I got home. I was pretty easily able to find a description on the Denver Department of Public Health &amp;amp; Environment (DDPHE)&amp;rsquo;s website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the next week&amp;rsquo;s research group meeting, I mentioned the initiative to Colleen and wondered out loud whether analyzing data from such a program could potentially be a collaboration for our group. She said that she knew the head of the program, and asked if I would like to set up a call with them. Over the ensuing Skype call with the head of the DDPHE air quality program, it turned out that DDPHE had access to asthma medication usage records from Denver Public Schools (DPS) in addition to air pollution measurements from their low-cost sensor network, but didn&amp;rsquo;t yet have anyone analyzing the data. They were enthusiastic about us analyzing the data for them, especially when we proposed that I could apply for undergraduate research funding through the university so that they didn&amp;rsquo;t have to pay me. Thus began a collaboration through which I learned a lot about air quality sensors and statistical methods to make the low-cost sensor measurements more accurate, and Colleen and I were able to advise DDPHE and DPS on how best to correct their air pollution measurements and how to record/aggregate future data on asthma rescue medication usage to make it most useful for health studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;story-3-how-i-developed-a-leadership-role-in-cu-engineers-without-borders-ewb&#34;&gt;Story #3: How I Developed a Leadership Role in CU Engineers Without Borders (EWB)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every organization has unique ins and outs, but I am willing to bet that the majority of volunteer-based organizations conform to the following statement: the more time you spend in attendance at meetings and events and the more questions you ask, the faster you will become a member of the functional core (the people who know stuff and get things done). This was certainly true of my experience with EWB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my first semester of college, after being inspired to get involved with EWB, I showed up to a lot of meetings, including student-only ones on weeknights and meetings with a group of professional mentors every other Sunday at 8am in the CU Engineering Center lobby. Because I was in attendance, because I was attuned and asking questions and volunteering to do random tasks, I became one of the most involved first-year students and ended up being selected to join the summer travel team to Nepal. Upon my return from Nepal, I continued being present at both student-only and mentor meetings. I won&amp;rsquo;t go into all the details here, but my experiences with EWB (including getting to know people in that extensive community) were some of the most valuable of my whole college experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;caveat&#34;&gt;Caveat&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, not every interaction will yield a tangible result &amp;ndash; the idea is that over time, one becomes better positioned to benefit from circumstance: as they say, luck favors the well-prepared!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, as convinced as I am of the power of showing up and reaching out, I recognize the bias of my perspective due to my background. For thoughts in this vein, see my &amp;ldquo;Reflections on Privilege in Higher Education&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Others&#39; Ideas that Resonate</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/project/ideas_resonate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/project/ideas_resonate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are lists of articles, podcasts, videos, etc. that I intend to continuously update as I come across well-explained, powerful ideas that relate directly to my field(s) of interest. For the most part, these resources are more conversational than technical, and are meant to inspire as well as inform. Also see my list of recommended nonfiction books, which spans a larger range of topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;environmental-health&#34;&gt;Environmental Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessing the health burden from air pollution &amp;ndash; Science perspective, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;StoryMap: &amp;ldquo;Air Pollution and Health: The Global Impacts of Fossil Fuels&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; State of Global Air, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaging Socially Vulnerable Communities and Communicating About Climate Change &amp;ndash; NASEM, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leveraging Air Quality Research Advancements to Assess and Address Exposure Inequities &amp;ndash; Goldman, 2023. Environmental Health Perspectives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are “safe” exposure levels really “safe”? &amp;ndash; Program on Reproductive Health and the Environment, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Western lawmakers spot opening in smoke crisis &amp;ndash; Axios, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A conversation on air pollution in the United States &amp;ndash; Nature Geoscience, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naming civic health in environmental justice discourse: The Jackson water crisis &amp;ndash; Nwanaji-Enwerem &amp;amp; Casey, 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flipping the Climate Debate from Costs to Benefits &amp;ndash; Anenberg, 2021. Environmental Health News&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tackling Air Pollution and Climate Justice Together &amp;ndash; Moses &amp;amp; Roy, 2021. Environmental Defense Fund&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Closing the Data Gap: A Cost-Effective Way to Improve [Global] Air Quality &amp;ndash; Hasenkopf, 2021. World Economic Forum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Air Pollution Diminishes Future Generations&amp;rsquo; Economic Opportunities &amp;ndash; Voorheis, 2021. US Census&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Feedback to Improve Accountability in Global Environmental Health and Engineering &amp;ndash; Thomas &amp;amp; Brown, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is AI revolutionizing environmental health? (Simply Statistics &amp;ndash; Peng, 2019). In general, this blog has a lot of cool posts for data scientists and educators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Environmental Health Disparities - An Overview (Harvard Chan NIEHS Center for Environmental Health) &amp;ndash; Mendonça, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ClimateBits: Unhealthy Air &amp;ndash; 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is Environmental Health? &amp;ndash; YouTube, NYU School of Global Public Health, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Podcasts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agents of Change in Environmental Justice &amp;ndash; podcast featuring emerging leaders from historically excluded backgrounds in science and academia who are reimagining solutions for a just and healthy planet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is Your Brain on Pollution &amp;ndash; Freakonomics podcast, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Data Science to Study Air Pollution&amp;rsquo;s Effect on Covid-19 (Women in Data Science podcast) &amp;ndash; Dominici &amp;amp; Nethery, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Atmospheric Tales &amp;ndash; podcast discussing global environmental health, 2020 onwards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decolonizing Air Pollution Science &amp;ndash; deSouza, 2020 / MIT Community Innovators Lab (CoLab) Radio (overall archive). Stories and reflections on the interplay of science and technology with community development and planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feature-length / series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How air pollution impacts our brains, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NASEM Climate Crossroads Summit 2023 (video playlist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NASEM Workshop on Communities, Climate Change, and Health Equity – Lessons Learned in Addressing Inequities in Heat-Related Climate Change Impacts (2023)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HSPH Climate, Health, &amp;amp; Equity Symposium 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Health Effects Institute (HEI) Science on the 7th &amp;ndash; series discussing current critical topics in air quality and global health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearing the Air: Why Now Is the Time to Tackle Global Air Pollution &amp;ndash; HSPH + WHO + CNN, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking the Temperature: Your Health, Our Climate, and What We Can Do About It &amp;ndash; Mazumder, 2021. Harvard Science in the News series.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Story of Plastic (2019). Documentary examining issues and opportunities throughout the lifecycle of plastic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dark Waters (2019). Dramatic recreation of Rob Bilott&amp;rsquo;s case against the chemical manufacturing company DuPont after they contaminated a town with unregulated chemicals. &lt;em&gt;For more information on the environmental health science occurring behind the scenes, check out the C8 Science Panel website.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative on Health and the Environment: Climate Change and Health, 2019. Collection of videos, focusing on the topics of extreme heat, air pollution, extreme weather events, and infectious diseases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Crowd &amp;amp; the Cloud &amp;ndash; Abdalati, 2017. Video series discussing citizen science used in environmental health applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-science--statistics&#34;&gt;Data Science / Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big data in Earth science: Emerging practice and promise &amp;ndash; Science review, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Democratizing the future of AI R&amp;amp;D: NSF to launch National AI Research Resource pilot (2024)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What Should Data Science Education Do with Large Language Models? &amp;ndash; Tu et al, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NASA and IBM Openly Release Geospatial AI Foundation Model for NASA Earth Observation Data (2023)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strengthening [global] public health systems through artificial intelligence &amp;ndash; HSPH, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvard Graduate Transforms High School Math Curriculum: Skew The Script, a nonprofit organization, provides free, socially-relevant math + statistics lessons to high school teachers across the country &amp;ndash; Harvard Data Science Initiative, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple Women’s Health Study advances understanding of menstrual cycles and health (2023) &amp;ndash;Example of thoughtful data collection generating insights that are highly relevant for both clinicians and policy makers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there a role for statistics in artificial intelligence? &amp;ndash; Friedrich et al, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the Most Important Statistical Ideas of the Past 50 Years? &amp;ndash; Gelman &amp;amp; Vehtari, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Artificial Intelligence&amp;rsquo;s Promise &amp;amp; Peril (2021) &amp;ndash; Harvard School of Public Health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter thread: best data visualizations (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What Are the Values of Data, Data Science, or Data Scientists? &amp;ndash; Meng, 2021. Harvard Data Science Review editorial piece.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistics Monitors the Environment and Statistics Informs Health Policy &amp;ndash; ASA Statistical Significance Series&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ASCCR Frame for Learning Essential Collaboration Skills &amp;ndash; Vance &amp;amp; Smith, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Career of Gertrude M. Cox &amp;ndash; NC State Library&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Podcasts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mental Health Challenges: How Can Data Science Help? &amp;ndash; Harvard Data Science Review Podcast, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Casual Inference podcast by Ellie Murray and Lucy D&amp;rsquo;Agostino McGowan, specifically this episode featuring Roger Peng: &amp;ldquo;Why Everyone is Excited About Causal Inference These Days&amp;rdquo; (2020)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feature-length / series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shaping the Future of AI &amp;ndash; National Academies; one insightful discussion can be found in the &amp;ldquo;Navigating Ethical Dilemmas&amp;rdquo; section in this article&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop Explaining Black Box Machine Learning Models for High Stakes Decisions and Use Interpretable Models Instead (Harvard Data Science Initiative Bias^2 seminar) &amp;ndash; Rudin, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;career--miscellaneous&#34;&gt;Career / Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Human Implications of AI with Brian Christian &amp;ndash; NASEM, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time to support Indigenous science &amp;ndash; Wall Kimmerer &amp;amp; Artelle, 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are you saving the world? &amp;ndash; Parast, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the evidence-based advice we found on how to be more successful in any job &amp;ndash; Todd (80,000 Hours), 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Field-Specific Ability Beliefs as an Explanation for Gender Differences in Academics’ Career Trajectories: Evidence From Public Profiles on ORCID.org &amp;ndash; Hannak et al, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing Women’s Representation in STEM Fields &amp;ndash; Gray, 2023&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which food is better for the planet? &amp;ndash; Washington Post Climate Lab (2023). Interactive visualizations comparing different food types over various environmental dimensions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A list of the most high-impact, evidence-based organizations fighting climate change &amp;ndash; Samuel, 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rethinking international development strategy—and hearing echoes of global challenges in the United States &amp;ndash; Harvard Kennedy School faculty, 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impostors Anonymous &amp;ndash; Witten, 2022. Helpful thoughts on impostor syndrome in academia / high-achievement communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My experience with imposter syndrome—and how to (partly) overcome it &amp;ndash; Rodriguez (80,000 Hours), 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Americans experience a false social reality by underestimating popular climate policy support by nearly half &amp;ndash; Sparkman, Geiger, &amp;amp; Weber, 2022.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In academia, we need two types of researchers: divers and surfers &amp;ndash; Pandya, 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Putting Mental Health in America on the Map &amp;ndash; Geraghty (ESRI), 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Public Health Took Part in Its Own Downfall &amp;ndash; The Atlantic, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effective Altruism: An Update to Our Thinking On Climate Change &amp;ndash; Ackva, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Five Ways To Prioritize Better &amp;ndash; Bye, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200 Years in 4 Minutes &amp;ndash; Rosling, 2017. Global relationships between lifespan and income over time, across countries. Note: there are many videos of Rosling presenting other cool data visualizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Podcasts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Degrees of Freedom &amp;ndash; Hasenkopf, 2020. Exploring many different ways that scientists can have positive impact through their careers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AAAS STPF Sci on the Fly. A variety of science and policy topics, written by scientists working in the federal government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feature-length / series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvard School of Public Health YouTube Channel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science x Policy Crossroads: Pathways toward Health Policy &amp;ndash; ten people&amp;rsquo;s stories illustrating different careers at the intersection of science and policy, put together by the National Science Policy Network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AAAS Voices: Countering Science Misinformation (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
