<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Remote Sensing | Ellen Considine</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/remote-sensing/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/tags/remote-sensing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Remote Sensing</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:4321/media/icon_hu68170e94a17a2a43d6dcb45cf0e8e589_3079_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Remote Sensing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/remote-sensing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upper Division Course Projects at Harvard and CU Boulder</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/project/course_projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/project/course_projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To provide a sense of what I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on other than my research in the National Studies on Air Pollution &amp;amp; Health Group and Earth Lab, here is a list of my most substantial projects that resulted in course papers but not peer-reviewed publications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reviewed state-of-the-art offline reinforcement learning algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigated the usefulness of Bayesian Additive Regression Trees (BART) for estimating
uncertainty in wildfire smoke prediction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explored methods to deal with measurement error (noise) in longitudinal (correlated) data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used distributed lag nonlinear models to investigate associations between air pollution and mortality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explored the evolution of discourse surrounding global public health surveillance and
information systems, including future opportunities and risks in implementation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used network methods, spatial and socioeconomic data to model migration between U.S. cities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used data assimilation methods to model seasonal flu cases in Denver, CO&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used spatial kriging to improve estimation of air quality from a random forest model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used satellite imagery to analyze trends in air quality over Southeast Asia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used a hierarchical model and change-point analysis to predict energy usage from
temperature in U.S. cities. &lt;em&gt;My model was the class’s most accurate on unseen data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used a convolutional neural network to predict sociodemographic information based on
satellite images of US cities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
