<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Public Health | Ellen Considine</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/public-health/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/tags/public-health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Public Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:4321/media/icon_hu68170e94a17a2a43d6dcb45cf0e8e589_3079_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Public Health</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/public-health/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying for the NSF GRFP</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/nsf-grfp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/nsf-grfp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a ton of general information online about the National Science Foundation (NSF) Graduate Research Fellowship, so I won&amp;rsquo;t go into many details here. For a large, high-quality collection of advice and past examples across fields, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.alexhunterlang.com/nsf-fellowship&#34;&gt;Alex Lang&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for folks interested in statistics/data science/AI applied to public health, a couple more tailored insights may be valuable. For context: I applied for the GRFP during my senior year of undergrad (fall of 2019). I am now entering my fifth and final year of a PhD program in Biostatistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;to-what-extent-should-i-focus-on-public-health-in-my-application&#34;&gt;To what extent should I focus on public health in my application?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One part of the GRFP solicitation that can trip people up is the section on &amp;ldquo;Ineligible areas of study&amp;rdquo; and the related section on &amp;ldquo;Limited exceptions to ineligible research&amp;rdquo;. Here are some text excerpts from 2024:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i. &amp;ldquo;Individuals are not eligible to apply if they will be enrolled in graduate study focused on clinical practice, counseling, social work, patient-oriented research, epidemiological and medical behavioral studies,
outcomes research (interventions, treatment, or therapies), and health services research. Ineligible study
includes pharmacologic, non-pharmacologic, and behavioral interventions for physical or mental disease
or disorder, prophylaxis, diagnosis, therapy, or treatment. Research to provide evidence leading to a
scientific basis for consideration of a change in health policy or standard of care is not eligible. Graduate
study focused on community, public, or global health, or other population-based research including
medical intervention trials is also not eligible.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ii. &amp;ldquo;For applicants applying to degree programs in engineering, mathematical, physical, computer or
information sciences disciplines, research with disease- or health-related goals (e.g., etiology-, diagnosis-,
or treatment-related) that &lt;strong&gt;advance fundamental knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; in engineering, mathematical, physical,
computer or information sciences, is eligible for support.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is: &lt;em&gt;what is an appropriate balance between focusing on health vs the fundamental knowledge&lt;/em&gt;? Some advice I was given while applying was to keep in mind that the National Institutes of Health (NIH) have a lot of funding and their own graduate fellowship(s), so you have to make the case that NSF should care about your work in this ecosystem. When I was writing my application, I tried to emphasize the statistical questions / proposed contributions, using the public health question(s) as motivation throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;my-application-materials&#34;&gt;My application materials&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a concrete example, &lt;a href=&#34;./ConsidineEM_GRFP_Research_Proposal.pdf&#34;&gt;here is my research proposal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For additional context, &lt;a href=&#34;./ConsidineEM_GRFP_application_review.pdf&#34;&gt;here are the reviews  I received&lt;/a&gt;, which also provide some documentation of my CV at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-similar-is-my-dissertation-to-my-grfp-proposal-from-5-years-ago&#34;&gt;How similar is my dissertation to my GRFP proposal from 5 years ago?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As emphasized throughout GRFP advice forums, this fellowship invests in the person, not the project. For a sense of how much your ideas can change / be refined (especially if you are applying as an undergrad), I encourage you to read the abstract of &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36623253/&#34;&gt;my first dissertation paper&lt;/a&gt;, which was originally based on my GRFP research proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the rest of my dissertation falls under the umbrella of statistics/data science for environmental health (consistent with the goals stated throughout my GRFP application), the topics of my second and third papers are quite different than my GRFP research proposal, in part because they explore methodological areas that I was unfamiliar with / unaware of before starting grad school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, as long as you genuinely represent your goals, your specific research ideas can (and likely will!) evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Fellow for Graduate-Level Biostatistics Courses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/project/tf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/project/tf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are descriptions of the three full-semester courses that I helped teach at HSPH.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;spring-2024-bst-226-applied-longitudinal-analysis&#34;&gt;Spring 2024: BST 226, Applied Longitudinal Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approx. number of students: 100&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Course description: This course covers modern methods for the analysis of repeated measures, correlated outcomes and longitudinal data, including the unbalanced and incomplete data sets characteristic of biomedical research. Topics include an introduction to the analysis of correlated data, analysis of response profiles, fitting parametric curves, covariance pattern models, random effects and growth curve models, and generalized linear models for longitudinal data, including generalized estimating equations (GEE) and generalized linear mixed effects models (GLMMs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fall-2023-bst-210-applied-regression-analysis&#34;&gt;Fall 2023: BST 210, Applied Regression Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approx. number of students: 75&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Course description: Topics include model interpretation, model building, and model assessment for linear regression with continuous outcomes, logistic regression with binary outcomes, and proportional hazards regression with survival time outcomes. Specific topics include regression diagnostics, confounding and effect modification, goodness of fit, data transformations, splines and additive models, ordinal, multinomial, and conditional logistic regression, generalized linear models, overdispersion, Poisson regression for rate outcomes, hazard functions, and missing data. The course provides students with the skills necessary to perform regression analyses and to critically interpret statistical issues related to regression applications in the public health literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fall-2021-bst-222-basics-of-statistical-inference&#34;&gt;Fall 2021: BST 222, Basics of Statistical Inference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approx. number of students: 75&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Course description: This course provides a basic yet thorough introduction to the probability theory and mathematical statistics that underlie many of the commonly used techniques in public health research. Topics covered include probability distributions (normal, binomial, Poisson), means, variances and expected values, finite sampling distributions, parameter estimation (method of moments, maximum likelihood), confidence intervals, hypothesis testing (likelihood ratio, Wald and score tests). All theoretical material are motivated with problems from epidemiology, biostatistics, environmental health and other public health areas. This course is aimed towards second year doctoral students in fields other than Biostatistics. Background in algebra and calculus required.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science in the News Talk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/project/sitn/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/project/sitn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I leveraged the material from my HPHR blog, as well as new content, to give a public-facing talk on air pollution, global health, data science, and public policy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathing Data Blog</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/project/breathing_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/project/breathing_data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2021, I wrote a series of blog posts on air pollution, global health, and data science for &lt;em&gt;HPHR Journal&lt;/em&gt;, formerly the &lt;em&gt;Harvard Public Health Review&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover image from PurpleAir map on June 7, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Principled Negotiation and the Ethos of Public Health</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/public-health-ethos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/public-health-ethos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am currently reading a book on negotiation called &lt;em&gt;Getting to Yes&lt;/em&gt;, written by members of the Harvard Negotiation Project. One of the opening chapters describes positional bargaining: two sides starting from places of disagreement and inching their way closer by making small concessions in turn. The authors describe how problematic this process is: it is inefficient, commonly leads to unwise outcomes (good for neither side), and can harm relationships between parties. Instead, the book presents a case for principled negotiation, founded on separating the people (negotiators) from the problem, focusing on interests instead of positions, inventing options for mutual gain, and insisting on use of objective criteria. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pon.harvard.edu/daily/negotiation-skills-daily/principled-negotiation-focus-interests-create-value/&#34;&gt;Here is a nice summary&lt;/a&gt;, for those interested in learning more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bring this book up to motivate presentation of my principles. Nearly everything we do in our professional and personal lives is a negotiation of some kind. It is important to establish what we believe so that we can work with others to identify common ground and develop pragmatic solutions to our problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listening to the news and having conversations with other people, it is clear that there are foundationally diverse beliefs about how human civilization should look, and how we should get there (if the belief is that we aren&amp;rsquo;t already there). I have come to the unoriginal conclusion that the largest discrepancy in how people think and act is described by the weight an individual mentally assigns to their personal freedoms in comparison with the freedoms of others, and to what extent they believe we should rely on governmental authorities to enforce the balance of individuals&amp;rsquo; freedoms. This discrepancy has obvious ties to the arena of public health, where large and complex problems such as infectious diseases and environmental pollution bring tensions between individual freedoms and collective sacrifice to light. In fact, while pondering my beliefs and their implications, I ran across the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apha.org/-/media/files/pdf/membergroups/ethics/code_of_ethics.ashx&#34;&gt;Public Health Code of Ethics&lt;/a&gt; by the American Public Health Association (APHA) and determined this to be the most clear articulation of my principles that I have ever found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an excerpt from this Code of Ethics [page 3, bolding is mine], defining what it means for humans to flourish:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Flourishing does not focus so much on biological function as on &lt;strong&gt;the social conditions of capability and opportunity&lt;/strong&gt; upon which health itself and many other goods depend. Flourishing refers to what individuals and communities experience when institutional and cultural structures create the opportunity for people to realize a wide range of potential capabilities inherent in all human beings. Flourishing occurs when &lt;strong&gt;capabilities for agency, creativity, intelligence, understanding, emotional engagement, and other positive human potentialities take shape in the form of lives well lived&lt;/strong&gt;. As such, we take a life course perspective that examines public health issues from maternal and child health into old age while &lt;strong&gt;recognizing specific vulnerabilities&lt;/strong&gt; at the extremes of age. The term human flourishing also underscores the &lt;strong&gt;relational interdependence&lt;/strong&gt; among human beings, which is expressed in virtually all social and cultural activity and fits well with the contemporary understanding of the social determinants of health. &lt;strong&gt;The preconditions of everyone’s health are communal and systemic&lt;/strong&gt;, and the field of public health must address them as such. Human flourishing is thus consonant with a social-relational, rather than an exclusively individualistic, interpretation of key values such as human rights, liberty, equality, and social and environmental justice that play a vital role in contemporary public health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The opposite of human flourishing is&lt;/strong&gt; not only disease or ill health but also domination, inequity, discrimination, exploitation, exclusion, suffering, and despair: in a word, &lt;strong&gt;the stultification and denial of optimal human self-realization and thriving human communities.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this definition, it is clear that public health is all about giving people opportunities to live fulfilling lives. In fact, it seems that the goal is to maximize individual freedoms, within the bounds of not denying other individuals their freedoms. Later in this document, there is also an explicit discussion of responsibilities towards future generations and other organisms in our environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recognize that these statements may all seem abstract. However, I think that before moving to more specific examples, we need to identify foundational points of agreement, such as the preciousness of self-realization. Then, we can build upon those foundations and deal with higher-level disagreements (e.g. differences in perspective about how we best allow people to self-realize) as they come. In the midst of extreme political polarization and ever-increasing complexity of societal problems, I believe that this kind of principled negotiation is necessary to develop a modern society that is just and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you too are someone who is interested in helping address large and complex issues in our society, I encourage you to articulate: what are your principles?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
